اَلْحَمْدَ لِلّهِ نَحْمَدُهُ وَنَسْتَعِينينُهُ وَنَسْتَغْفِرُهُ وَنَتُوْبُ اِلَيْه،
وَنَعُوذُ بِاللهِ مِنْ شُرُورِ أَنْفُسِنَا وَمِنْ سَيِّئَاتِ أَعْمَالِنَا،
مَنْ يَهْدِهِ اللهُ فَلاَ مُضِلَّ لَهُ، وَمَنْ يُضْلِلْ فَلاَ هَادِىَ لَهُ،
وَأَشْهَدُ أَنْ لاَ إِلَهَ إِلاَّ اللهُ وَحْدَهُ لاَ شَرِيكَ لَهُ،
وَأَشْهَدُ أَنَّ مُحَمَّدًا عَبْدُهُ وَرَسُولُهُ صَل اللهِ عَلَيْهِ وَعَلى أله وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلّمَ وَبَعْد
As we all have heard، the topic which will be discussed tonight, is a topic which is from the center of our beliefs.
It is a topic rooted in the Qur'an Allah's final revelation.
It is a topic that begins with the beginning of revelation to Allah's Prophet, Ibrahim عليه السلام
and continues until the day of judgment with the return of the Prophet Eesa عليه السلام,
passing through the Qur'an and the Sunnah(سنۃ) and the Seerah(سیرۃ) of our Prophet, the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ.
It is a topic which cannot be separated from our testimony of faith.
لا اله الا الله محمد الرسول الله
There is none worthy of worship but Allah and Muhammad ﷺ is the Messenger of Allah.
It is a topic which is part of the cancer which the Muslims suffer from today.
And it is a topic which, unless we find a cure for it, we will not find a cure for other ills that we suffer from.
The topic is great indeed.
The topic deserves a whole conference, not just merely a lecture,
and the topic deserves people of knowledge and honor to discuss it.
However we ask Allah عزوجل to assist us, in order that we may perhaps convey to our brothers and sisters some knowledge regarding this topic,
even though we ourselves are not from those, who deserve to discuss a topic of this importance.
In order to understand the situation in Palestine, one must begin with the matter of our faith, the essence of our belief, Tawheed(توحيد).
For as we all know Allah عزوجل has created us for a noble purpose.
Allah has created humanity and every single human being, indeed the jinns, for a great reason.
وَمَا خَلَقْتُ الْجِنَّ وَ الْاِنْسَ اِلَّا لِیَعْبُدُوْنِ۝
I have not created jinns nor human beings but to worship Me.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has sent His Messengers as ones giving glad tidings and warning for this purpose,
وَ لَقَدْ بَعَثْنَا فِیْ كُلِّ اُمَّةٍ رَّسُوْلًا اَنِ اعْبُدُوا اللّٰهَ وَ اجْتَنِبُوا الطَّاغُوْتَۚ
And We have sent to every single people a messenger, ordering that messenger to preach worship Allah alone and avoid the worship of a Tagoot(طاغوت),
all that is worshiped besides Allah.
And indeed Allah's revelation is centered upon this principle.
Throughout the Qur'an, we find the command to worship Allah and to avoid the worship of others.
وَعْبُدُوا اللّٰهَ وَ لَا تُشْرِكُوْا بِهٖ شَیْــٴًـا وَ قَضٰى رَبُّكَ اَلَّا تَعْبُدُوْۤا اِلَّاۤ اِیَّاهُ
And worship Allah alone and avoid the worship of others with Him.
And your Lord has decreed that you worship, only but Him; and so forth and so on.
And in the Sunnah(سنۃ) likewise, we find that our Prophet, the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ stressing this principle over and over.
One day his companion Muaaz bin Jabal رضي الله عنه is riding behind him on a donkey
and the Prophet ﷺ says,
O Muaaz(معاذ)! Do you know, when Allah's right is upon the creation?
Muaaz(معاذ) says Allah and His Messenger know best.
The Prophet ﷺ responds that His right meaning, Allah is right upon His creation is that His creation worship Him alone and does not associate anything with Him.
And then the Prophet ﷺ asked Muaaz(معاذ), and do you know what is the creations right upon Allah if they do that?
Muaaz(معاذ) replies Allah and His Messenger knows best.
The Prophet ﷺ says; Their right upon Allah that Allah will not punish them, if they do that.
This message of Tawheed(توحيد) for which We have been created,
for which Allah سبحانه وتعالى has sent His messengers,
for which Allah has sent down His scriptures,
and upon which Allah will judge every human being on the Day of Judgment, is the issue of Palestine.
It is an issue of Tawheed(توحيد) and Shirk(شرک).
It is an issue of Eeman(ایمان) and Kufr(کفر).
It is not an issue of nationalism or one race against another race, or one political philosophy against another political philosophy,
but it is an issue of truth and falsehood.
It is an issue that begins with the father of the prophets, humanity's third father,
the Prophet Ibrahim عليه السلام continuing to our Prophet, the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ, and concluding with the Prophet Eesa عليه السلام.
And in order to understand this issue, we must understand one aspect of Tawheed(توحيد);
and that is that Allah سبحانه وتعالى, like He is the creator, He also is the One, Who selects.
As Allah سبحانه وتعالى says,
وَ رَبُّكَ یَخْلُقُ مَا یَشَآءُ وَ یَخْتَارُؕ-مَا كَانَ لَهُمُ الْخِیَرَةُؕ-سُبْحٰنَ اللّٰهِ وَ تَعٰلٰى عَمَّا یُشْرِكُوْنَ۝
Allahسبحانه وتعالى in Surat-Ul-Qasas(سورۃ القصص) says;
And your Lord creates what He wills and chooses,
they have no choice in the matter.
Glory be to Allah and exalted from that which they associate unto Him.
So Allah سبحانه وتعالى, as He is the Creator, He is also the One, Who chooses and selects from His creation.
He has selected from His creation that the angels live in the heavens above,
and from the angels, He has selected Jibrail(جبرائیل) and Mikail(میکائیل) and Israfil علیہم السلام.
He has selected from the creatures, on those who are upon earth human beings, and Has selected from the human beings, the prophets.
And selected from the prophets the messengers,
and selected from the messengers, those five messengers of resolute determination.
اُولُوا الْعَزْمِ مِنَ الرُّسُلِ
the prophets Noah عليه السلام and Ibrahim عليه السلام and Musa عليه السلام and Eesa Ibn-E-Maryam عليه السلام and our Prophet, the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ.
And from those five messengers, He has chosen His two Khalil(خلیل)s, Ibrahim(ابراھیم) and Muhammad صلی اللہ علیہما وسلمہ.
And likewise from humanity, indeed, from everything He has chosen the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ, and selected him to be the master of all human beings, the leader of all humanity,
as the Prophet ﷺ has said;
أنَا سَيِّدُ وَلَدِ آدَمَ وَلَا فَخْرَ
I am the master or the best of the children of Adam(آدم) and I say this not, out of a statement of boast.
Likewise Allah سبحانه وتعالى choses certain times.
In the week he has chosen the day of Al Jumua(جمعہ) as a day, when which we worship Him and remember His creation.
For Allah سبحانه وتعالى created the heavens and the earth in six days, the final day being the day of Jumuaa(جمعہ)
And it is the day in which He has created Adam, and it is the day in which the Day of Judgment will occur.
So Allah has selected this day as the day of our weekly worship.
And likewise, He has chosen amongst the months, four months that are holy months,
Muharram(محرم) and Rajab(رجب) and Zul Qada(ذوالقعدہ) and Zul Hijja(ذوالحجہ).
And He has also chosen amongst the months Ramadan(رمضان)
as the month in which we fast and in the month which we worship Him, and in the month which He revealed the Qur'an.
And among nights, He chose Lelat-Ul-Qadar(لیلۃ القدر).
And likewise Allah سبحانه وتعالى has chosen places.
He has selected places in which He has honored and has set up for His worship alone.
He chose the lands of Mecca,
and in Mecca, He chose a certain Valley in which His house was erected for His worship, the Ka’aba(کعبہ).
And He chose the lands of Medina.
And in Medina, He chose a certain part between its two valleys, in which the Prophet's Masjid was erected صلی اللہ علیہ وسلم.
And likewise, He chose the lands of Ash-Sham(الشام), the lands of Syria.
And from there, He chose specifically a certain city Bait-Al Maqdas(بیت المقدس).
And from there He chose a certain hill, upon which Allah decreed that another Masjid(مسجد) be built, Masjid-Al-Aqsa(اقصی).
This is part of Tawheed(توحيد).
And this is why Allah سبحانه وتعالى made it part of our religion that one cannot set out in a journey for worship, except to these three Masajid(مساجد).
And the prayers in these Masajid(مساجد) are multiplied in terms of its reward,
and there are certain etiquettes and certain rewards that are connected with these three Masajid(مساجد),
which are not connected with any other place on earth.
And so therefore, to separate Masjid-Al-Aqsa(مسجد الاقصی) from Mecca and Medina, it is as if to separate part of Islam from another part.
We are an Ummah(امۃ) of Tawheed(توحيد).
We are an Ummah(امۃ) which follows the prophets.
Do you not see that the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ, when he found the Jews fasting the day of Ashura (عاشورہ),
he inquired what day is this?
They said, this is a noble day in which Allah سبحانه وتعالى rescued Moses from Pharaoh.
What did the Prophet ﷺ said; We are more deserving of Moses then them.
And likewise, Allah in the Qur'an has informed us, that
the Prophet Ibrahim عليه السلام was neither a Jew nor a Christian, nor from the pagans, but he ever, he was a Muslim, a Hanif(حنیف),
and he was not from the pagans worshiping Allah alone.
And Allah tells us that the one, who is closest to Ibrahim عليه السلام were his immediate followers, and this prophet and the believers,
meaning the Ummah of Muhammad ﷺ.
And do you not see, how Eesa عليه السلام, when he returns at the end of time, he returns as a Messenger,
but judging by the Qur'an and the Sunnah, not with a new Sharia(شریعہ),
not ruling by the law, which was sent down to him, of the Injeel(انجیل) or of the Torah(توراۃ),
but rather, as the Prophet ﷺ said؛ As a just ruler in this Ummah(امۃ).
So the Ummah(امۃ) of Muhammad ﷺ, we are the believers in all the revelation of Allah,
and we are the believers in all the prophets of Allah.
And so therefore to separate parts of the places, which Allah has honored through some of his prophets،
is as if we were to believe in part of the message and disbelieve in part of the message,
or believe in some of the messengers and disbelieve in the others of the messengers.
Baitul Maqdas, is connected to Mecca and Medina and can never be separated from it.
And the evidences upon this from the Quran and the Sunnah(سنۃ) are very many, and likewise from history.
And what we will do in the next few moments is review some of those evidences.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى in the Quran in five passages informs us that these lands of Ash-Sham(الشام),
these lands of Syria and Lebanon and Palestine and Jordan, are lands in which Allah سبحانه وتعالى has blessed.
And in the passage which I think most of us are most familiar with, in where Allah سبحانه وتعالى opens up,
starts Surat-Ul-Isra(سورۃ الاسراء), Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
سُبْحٰنَ الَّذِیْۤ اَسْرٰى بِعَبْدِهٖ لَیْلًا مِّنَ الْمَسْجِدِ الْحَرَامِ اِلَى الْمَسْجِدِ الْاَقْصَا الَّذِیْ بٰرَكْنَا حَوْلَهٗ
Glory be to Allah, Who took His servant meaning the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ, during a night journey from Masjid-Al-Haram from Mecca to Masjid-Al-Aqsa(مسجدالاقصی),
regarding which we have blessed the surrounding lands.
and the connection; there is also a deep lesson in this.
Not only is Allah سبحانه وتعالى teaching us, or telling us an event of the Prophet ﷺ life,
but as Shaykh Ul Islam Ibn Taymiyah(شَيْخُ الإِسْلَام اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّة) has said;
This also tells us the history of the Ummah(امۃ) in this, there is a deeper meaning.
For just like the message of Islam began in the time of the Prophet ﷺ, in Mecca,
it will come at the end of time and be in Jerusalem.
And just like the beginning of the Ummah(امۃ), just like Mecca is more preferred and beloved to Allah عزوجل than Jerusalem,
likewise the first of the Ummah(امۃ), meaning the Prophet ﷺ, his companions are better than those, who will be at the end of time, even though they will be with the Prophet Eesa عليه السلام.
And indeed in the Prophet Sunnah(سنۃ), we find many narrations in which the Prophet ﷺ has stressed the importance of Bait-Al-Maqdas(بیت المقدس).
For example we find that the Prophet ﷺ has said in one Hadith(حدیث).
The Hadith(حدیث) of Memoona(میمونہ), the freed slave woman of the Prophet ﷺ.
This is reported by Imam Ahmed(امام احمد);
She says; Oh Messenger of Allah, give us a Fatwa(فتوی); give us an answer regarding Bait-Al-Maqdas(بیت المقدس).
So even though Sahabah(صحابہ) used to question the Prophet ﷺ regarding Bait-Al-Maqdas(بیت المقدس)'s importance.
What did the Prophet ﷺ say, as reported by Imam Ahmad (امام احمد) in the Musnad(مسند) , he says;
ارض المحشر والمنشر
It is the land where the people will be gathered, and the land of the resurrection.
And then the Prophet ﷺ has said, come to it and pray there.
For a prayer, there is like a thousand prayers anywhere else,
and the meaning is anywhere else, outside of Mecca, Masjid Haram(مسجد الحرام), and Masjid Nabawi(مسجد النبوی) in Madina,
and then Memoona(میمونہ) said, and if I cannot reach Bait-Al-Maqdas(بیت المقدس), what should I do?
The Prophet ﷺ said, then give as an offering some oil by which you might light the Masjid(مسجد).
In other words, in the old days, before the advent of electricity, they would take oil and they would burn torches in order to give light in the Masajid(مساجد).
So here the Prophet ﷺ says to Memoona(میمونہ),
if you cannot reach Bait-Al-Maqdas(بیت المقدس), then send some oil there, in order to beautify that house of Allah عزوجل, so the people may pray there.
The people may recite the Qur'an there.
The people may do other acts of worship there.
And then the Prophet ﷺ said;
فمن فعل زلک
whoever does such, it is like the person, who has gone there and prayed.
And in another Hadith (حدیث) of the Prophet ﷺ;
The Prophet ﷺ was asked by Abu Zarr(ابوذر) what was the first Masjid(مسجد) built on earth.?
The Prophet ﷺ says, Masjid Al Haram(مسجدالحرام).
And the Hadith(حدیث) is in Bukhari(بخاری).
And then Abu Zarr(ابوذر) says, Then which Masjid(مسجد)?
The Prophet ﷺ says, Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصی) and there was fourty years between the two.
And likewise, the Prophet ﷺ teaches us another Hadith (حدیث) reported by Muslim(المسلم) upon his companion, Anas(انس).
The Prophet ﷺ says that the Buraaq(براق) which was the beast, which he rode for his Meraaj(معراج), was brought to him, and he rode it to Bait-Al-Maqdas(بیت المقدس).
And so then he tied the Buraaq(براق) to the ring in which the prophets would tie their animal, their horses and camels too.
And he entered into the Masjid(مسجد), and he prayed in their two Rakaats(رکعۃ), and then was raised to the heavens.
And indeed the Prophet ﷺ when he prayed in their two Rakaats(رکعۃ), he prayed with leading all the prophets of Allah,
as the prophet ﷺ tells us in other Hadith (حدیث).
The Prophet ﷺ into another narration reported by Imam Ahmed(امام احمد);
one of his companions by the name of  Zil Assabe(ذلاسابع), or Zul Assabe(ذولاسابع) asked the Prophet ﷺ says;
If we are tested, in other words, if we face a disaster, to live after you,
then what do you order us? What do you command us?
In other words, the Prophet's companions knew that to live after the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ, was a disaster, not to be in His presence.
What should we do if we're to live after you?
The Prophet ﷺ says,
علیک ببیت المقدس
it is upon you to go to the house of worship, the Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجد الاقصی) in Jerusalem,
and he says, For perhaps you might, will be given children who will then go there in morning and evening worshiping Allah there.
Indeed the Prophet ﷺ said;
In another Hadith(حدیث), he asked Abu Zarr(ابوذر),
he says to Abu Zarr(ابوذر) , he says, Oh Abu Zarr(ابوذر), what should you do if you are forced to leave Madina?
Abu Zarr(ابوذر) says, If I am forced to leave Madina, I will only leave Madina and I will go to Mecca, and I will be like the pigeons of Mecca,
meaning I will stick as a pigeon of Mecca always there in Masjid Al Haram(مسجد الحرام), I will be there.
So the Prophet ﷺ says to Abu Zarr(ابوذر); And what will you do if you're forced to leave Mecca?
Abu Zarr(ابوذر) said; I will then go to Ash-Sham(الشام) and to Bait-Ul-Maqdas(بیت المقدس).
And the Prophet ﷺ then asked Abu Zarr(ابوذر), what will you do if you're forced to leave Ash-Sham(الشام) and Bait-Ul-Maqdas(بیت المقدس)?
Abu Zarr(ابوذر) says, I will then put my sword on my shoulder, meaning I will go and wage Jihad(جہاد) wherever it takes me in the world.
And another Hadith(حدیث) of the Prophet ﷺ, Abdullah Bin Amr Bin Al-Aas(عبداللہ بن عمرو بن العاص) tells us the Prophet ﷺ Says;
There will be a Hijra(ھجرۃ) following a Hijra(ھجرۃ),
meaning that this Ummah(امۃ) will have Hijra(ھجرۃ) after Hijra(ھجرۃ) after Hijra(ھجرۃ) after Hijrah(ھجرۃ),
leaving the lands of the unbelievers، until going to the lands of Islam, just like they left Mecca; the Prophet ﷺ his companions and went to Madina.
This is something which will continue, Hijra(ھجرۃ) after Hijra(ھجرۃ) after Hijra(ھجرۃ),
until the people finally make Hijra(ھجرۃ) to the place that Ibrahim make Hijra(ھجرۃ)
meaning the land of Palestine, meaning the city of Jerusalem and the local areas thereabouts.
In another Hadith(حدیث), the Prophet ﷺ puts his hand upon his companion, Ibn Hawal Al Azdi(ابن حوال الازدی),
the Prophet ﷺ puts his hand on his head or on his forehead and says, Ibne Hawala (ابن حوالہ),
یا ابن الحوالہ
O son of Hawala(حوالہ), if you see the Khilafah(خلافہ) set up in Jerusalem,
then know the days of earthquakes and tribulations and great matters have come, and Hour will be closer to you, than my hand is to your head.
And likewise, the Prophet ﷺ we know from his Seerah(سیرۃ) that while in he was Mecca, he used to face Bait-Ul- Maqdas(بیت المقدس) in prayer.
And then after he made Hijra(ھجرۃ) for 16 months, as Ibn Abbas (ابن عباس) tells us,
he would face Bait-Ul- Maqdas(بیت المقدس) in prayer until the command came to him to face Mecca, the Ka'aba(کعبہ).
So the position of Palestine and these lands in the Qur'an and the Sunnah(سنۃ) cannot be denied.
And what I quoted of Hadith(حدیث) are just a few of the numerous Hadith(حدیث) regarding this land, which we will get into some other narrations as we go on in the lecture.
So the matter is not like as Daniel Pipes and other Zionists perceive.
When they say, you Muslims have Mecca; So why not give the Jews; Jerusalem?
Why not give Jerusalem to the Christians?
We can never do this, as we can never say we only believe in Muhammad ﷺ, and disbelief in Moses or Eesa علیہم السلام,
the two maters are tied to our faith.
Now, what is the history of this place, Palestine in particular, Jerusalem, Bait-Ul-Maqdas(بیت المقدس).
The history, as I mentioned, began with our father, the Prophet Ibrahim عليه السلام
for as you know, the Prophet Ibrahimعليه السلام was born in the lands of Iraq, on the Euphrates River.
And he called the people to Towheed(توحيد) there, and he broke the idols there.
And then he was commanded by Allah to migrate, to leave those lands, as Allah سبحانه وتعالى said;
وَ نَجَّیْنٰهُ وَ لُوْطًا
We rescued him and Lut(لوط) to the lands which We blessed, meaning the lands of Palestine and Ash-Shaam(الشام).
And from there Ibrahim عليه السلام made another journey.
He went to Egypt, after he was in Palestine, due to a drought,
but because of the oppressiveness of Pharaoh, as mentioned in the Hadith(حدیث),
he then had to leave that land, and he came back to Jerusalem.
And then finally, he went to Hijaz (حجاز), where he built, or rebuilt the Al-Kaaba(الکعبہ) with his son, Ismailعليه السلام.
But Ibrahim عليه السلام had another son.
Yes, he left Ismail(اسماعیل) and Hajar(ہاجر) in Mecca to establish, as Allah, mentions in the Qur'an,
to leave from his descendants, who would then establish the prayer.
But he had another son, the prophet Yaqoob عليه السلام,
and the Prophet Yaqoob(یعقوب) would worship Allah at the other place of worship, that Ibrahim عليه السلام established.
The Prophet Ishaq عليه السلام and the Prophet Yaqoob(یعقوب) worshiped Allah at the other house of worship, which the Prophet Ibrahim عليه السلام built
that is Masjid-Al-Aqsa(مسجد الاقصی) in Jerusalem.
And then we have the incident of the story of the Prophet Yousuf عليه السلام.
for the Prophet Yaqoobعليه السلام had 12 sons, and jealousy arose amongst the sons.
And we know the story, as Allah سبحانه وتعالى has described to us in the Qur'an and He said it's the most beautiful stories(احسن القصص),
the most beautiful of stories.
And what happens is that Yousuf عليه السلام ends up in Egypt and ends up at the end, as the governor of Egypt, عليه السلام
And he brings his father, the prophet Yaqoob(یعقوب), and his brothers to Egypt,
and the children of Israel, the children of Yaqoob(یعقوب) remain there for a period of time, as Allah سبحانه وتعالى  decrees for centuries,
until their fortunes reversed due to their leaving the revelation of Allah عزوجل, and they ended up in bondage, servitude and slavery to the Egyptians.
So Allah عزوجل sent to them, the Prophet Musaعلیہ السلام and the story of Musa(موسی) and Firaun(فرعون) is repeated over and over in the Qur'an, because there are many lessons in there.
There are many lessons dealing how to deal with tyrants in the story of Firaun(فرعون) Musaعلیہ السلام.
Allah told us these stories not only to show us
that how Musa(موسی) and the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ are resemble each other in revelation and in character and in message and in law,
but also it teaches us in these stories, lessons of the end of the tyrants,
because Firaun لعنہ اللہ was the greatest of tyrants.
And indeed, Allah سبحانه وتعالى tells us that after Musa علیہ السلام  and the children of Israel leave Egypt, as Allah mentions in this in Surat-Ul-Maeda(سورۃ الماءــدۃ),
Musa(موسٰی) tells his people.
یٰقَوْمِ ادْخُلُوا الْاَرْضَ الْمُقَدَّسَةَ الَّتِیْ كَتَبَ اللّٰهُ لَكُمْ
O my people enter into these holy lands which Allah has prescribed for you.
However, the children of Israel were not purified from their sins.
As Ibn Al-Qayyim رحمہ اللہ says;
They left; they crossed the sea; their feet had not dried, and they had begin to worship the calf.
So their hearts had not become pure yet, they were still affected by that environment of Egypt, that pagan environment.
And so they told Musa(موسٰی), we will not enter into that land.
فَاذْهَبْ اَنْتَ وَ رَبُّكَ فَقَاتِلَاۤ
Go you and your Lord and fight there; We will not enter that land.
So Allah سبحانه وتعالى  punished them by saying;
فَاِنَّهَا مُحَرَّمَةٌ عَلَیْهِمْ اَرْبَعِیْنَ سَنَةًۚ یَتِیْهُوْنَ فِی الْاَرْضِؕ
that it would be forbidden for them for 40 years, and they would be forced to wander upon the earth.
And the wisdom behind this is that Allahعزوجل wanted that generation, which was raised in bondage, which was raised amongst the pagans of Egypt to pass away.
And so when that generation passed away, after 40 years, a new generation comes,
and that generation enters into the holy lands, enters into the city of Jerusalem with the Prophet Yushua, or Joshua as we say it in English علیہ السلام.
But before that, there is an important incident which we should mention.
And that is that the Prophet Musa's علیہ السلام heart, like all the prophets of Allah, was clinging to this place.
For just like Musa's علیہ السلام heart was clinging to Mecca, it also was clinging to Jerusalem.
And so before Musaعلیہ السلام dies, Allah سبحانه وتعالى sends to him the angel of death.
And Musa(موسٰی) does not want to die, so he plucks out the eye of the angel of death,
and the Angel of Death returns back to its Lord, and Allah سبحانه وتعالى tells Musa death is something which is written upon every servant, and you must die,
but since you do not want to die, then put your hand on this, this oxen, this bull, and as many hairs as you pull out, you will live those many years extra.
And then Musa(موسٰی) asks, as a hadith(حدیث) is mentioned in Bukhari(البخاری);
Musa علیہ السلام then asks Allah, then what will happen?
Allah tells him, then death will come.
So Musa(موسٰی) says, Then, at least let me come close to the Holy Land, the stone throw away,
because it was forbidden for them to enter it.
But don't let me die far away from it; at least let me die that I'm a stone's throw away from the holy land.
The Prophet ﷺ said, if I was there, I would point to you where the grave of Musa(موسٰی) is.
It is by the Red Rock on the side of the road.
And so then the Prophet, after the 40 years is over, and the Prophet Musa علیہ السلام dies and is buried.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى sends the Prophet Yushua, who was a Prophet Musa's علیہ السلام helper, as mentioned in Surah Al-Kahf(سورۃ الکھف),
the young boy who was with Musa(موسٰی) when Musa(موسٰی) made that journey, to meet Al khaar(الخضر).
The Fataa(فتَی) was the prophet Yeshua, as mentioned the books of tafsir(تفسیر).
And here, the prophet Yeshua is commanded to enter into Jerusalem and to take Jerusalem before the day is over.
However, because of the sins of the children of Israel, as we will see,
they were unable to defeat the Phalistines, in that day.
And so the sun was about to set, and the battle was not over.
So the Prophet Yeshua looks to the sun and says,
أنکی مأمورةٌ وأنا مأمور
You are commanded by Allah, and I am also commanded.
So Allah holds the sun from setting, until they are able to enter into Jerusalem and take it, from the pagans.
However, the Jews were commanded, when upon entering into the city of Jerusalem to say;
قُوْلُوْا حِطَّةٌ
Say May Allah draw from us our sins.
نَّغْفِرْ لَكُمْ
We will forgive you from your sins.
However, the Jews did not say
حِطَّةٌ
They said;
حِنطَّةٌ
In their unbelief,
Instead of saying, May Allah draw from us our sins, they said;
حِنطَّةٌ
Which means wheat or barley, playing with Allah's words.
Anyway, Allah سبحانه وتعالى enters the children of Israel, and the Prophet Yushua.
And the other prophets lead them, as Prophet ﷺ said;
that the children of Israel were led by their prophets.
Whenever a prophet died, another prophet would come in charge.
And so you find the prophets leading the children of Israel and worshiping Allah in Masjid Al-Aqsa(مسجدالاقصی)
until we come another reference to the great prophet, the prophet Dawood علیہ السلام in the Qur'an.
Who Allah سبحانه وتعالى in Surat Saad(صٓ), tells us the story of the Prophet Dawood(داؤد) when he was in his Mehrab(محراب), in his prayer place,
meaning in Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجد الاقصی), praying there.
And the two people jump over there, and they say we have a dispute amongst ourselves.
In order to test the prophet Dawood(داؤد) the two angels as Allah mentions the story in Surat Saad(سورۃ صٓ).
And then we have after the Prophet Dawood علیہ السلام, we have his son, the Prophet Suleman علیہ السلام who also has a connection with Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجد الاقصی)
For as the Prophet ﷺ tells us, as reported by Imam Ahmed(امام احمد) in the Musnad(مسند), that Abdullah Bin Amr Bin Al Aas(عبداللہ بن عمرو بن العاص) reports to us
that the Prophet ﷺ  told us that after the Prophet Suleman(سلیمان) built Bait-Ul-Maqdas(بیت المقدس), rebuilt it and beautified it,
he asked Allah سبحانه وتعالى that Allah gives him three things,
and Allah سبحانه وتعالى granted for him two of those three things.
He asked Allah سبحانه وتعالى that he is given a judgment, which is in agreement with Allah's judgment.
So in other words, whatever the Prophet Suleman(سلیمان) will judge concerning something,
as he's a prophet, he's also a judge, that his ruling would be as Allah was, and Allah gave him that.
The Prophet ﷺ tells us that he also asked Allah for a kingdom that nobody would have after him.
And indeed Allah سبحانه وتعالى tells us this in the Qur'an in Surah Saad(صٓ) that He said;
رَبِّ اغْفِرْ لِیْ
Oh Allah forgive me.
وَهَبْ لِیْ مُلْكًا لَّا یَنْۢبَغِیْ لِاَحَدٍ مِّنْۢ بَعْدِیْۚ اِنَّكَ اَنْتَ الْوَهَّابُ۝
Oh Allah, forgive me my sin and give me a kingdom a dominion which will not be given to anybody after me.
You are the One, Who grants and bestows all things, You are Al Wahab(الوھاب).
And Suleman(سلیمان)'s kingdom was such that even the Jinn(جن)s were under his command and his orders.
His kingdom was such and his powers were such that he used to spend the morning in Jerusalem, and then when it would become hot,
he would come, as the scholars of Tafseer(تفسیر) say, and spend the afternoon in Kabul, in Afghanistan in the mountains, where it's cool.
Because the winds were under his command.
And then he asked (the Prophet ﷺ tells us) that the Prophet Suleman(سلیمان) asks Allah a third thing which Allah doesn't grant, the Prophet Suleman(سلیمان).
The Prophet Suleman(سلیمان) after building Bait-Ul-Maqdas(بیت المقدس), this Masjid-Al-Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی) says;
He asks Allah عزوجل, that any man, and man here means man or woman, come forth from their house, only wanting to pray in this house, in this Masjid(مسجد),
that he comes forth from his sins like the day his mother gives birth to him,
the Prophet, ﷺ  says and we hope that Allah gives us this
فنحن نرجو ان یکونو اللہ قد اطعنا ایاھا
And we hope that Allah عزوجل gives us this gift.
So look at this gift that the Prophet Suleman(سلیمان) asked of Allah عزوجل,
and the Prophet ﷺ says; We hope that Allah has given it to us, since he didn't give it to the Prophet Suleman(سلیمان)
that any one of us imagine now,
that if you were to go and leave your household, not wanting to do anything, but just to pray a Salah(صلاۃ) in this Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی),
that you would come out of that Masjid(مسجد) like the day your mother gave birth to you, meaning without sin.
We know that the difficulties of Hajj(حج), that Hajj(حج) right, the Hajj Al Mabroor(حج المبرور) the Prophet ﷺ said;
The blessed Hajj(حج) or the righteous Hajj(حج), is such that has no reward but paradise.
In another narration, it is the one, who does this Hajj(حج), and he does not enter into argument or does not enter into sinfulness,
he will be as the day in which his mother gave birth to him.
But Hajj(حج) is a difficult task.
It lasts for many days, and in order to hold yourself not to sin or not to get into dispute or argument is difficult
because it is something which goes on for many days,
but yet here you have the same reward for something which is much easier and takes much little time
just to go to this Masjid(مسجد) for the only purpose of doing prayer there, it doesn't have to be an obligatory prayer,
it can be a voluntary prayer, because the Hadith (حدیث) says Salah(صلاۃ) just in the absolute sense.
And this is why Ibn Umarرضی اللہ عنہ, knowing this Hadith(حدیث), leaves Madina and goes to Jerusalem
just to pray two Rakaah(رکعۃ)s and refuses to even drink a glass of water in the Masjid(مسجد)
and says, I want to go just for this reason.
So I have no other intention, and even though drinking water is obviously not something which is going to contradict praying.
For we know in our Sharia(شریعۃ) that in the Nafila(نافلۃ) prayer, in the non obligatory prayer, it is permissible to take small sips of water.
So one can even take a small sip of water in prayer, which means in Taraweeh(تراویح), if it's hot, you can take a small sip of water while you're praying.
And this doesn't negate your prayer.
Of course, in the obligatory prayer, to eat or to drink or to talk or to laugh, negates it.
But for the voluntary prayer, the conditions are not as stringent as as with the obligatory prayer,
yet Ibn Umar(ابنِ عمر) seeks not to even drink a water in Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی)
because he doesn't want it, in any way to affect his chance of winning this reward.
And so therefore, after the Prophet Suleman علیہ السلام, the children of Israel, of course, fall into great sin and go into idol worship.
So Allah عزوجل punishes them with the Babylonian,
or from Iraq, the person, Nebuchadnezzar, who comes and destroys Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی),
as Allah سبحانه وتعالى says in Surah Al Isra(سورہ الاسرا)؛;
that when the first promise comes, we will send to you people who are strong,
and they will come and they will destroy, they'll enter into your homes and destroy the Masjid(مسجد).
And he takes the children of Israel into captivity.
And there in captivity, they have many prophets among them, the prophet Daniaal or Daniel علیہ السلام, which we will refer to, at the end of the lecture.
And then Allah عزوجل  has mercy on the children of Israel, and they return back to Bait-Al-Maqdas(بیت المقدس).
And Allah sends them other prophets.
And we find again the Prophet ﷺ giving us more knowledge of the other prophets and what happens
for we find that Allah سبحانه وتعالى tells us the story of Maryam's mother, that she says when she is pregnant
اِنِّیْ نَذَرْتُ لَكَ مَا فِیْ بَطْنِیْ مُحَرَّرً
That I have given you Allah عزوجل as a vow.
What is in my belly,
meaning in order that what I'm going to give birth to, will must be in Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی) worshiping Allah عزوجل .
And that was?
She gave birth not to a boy but she gave birth to a girl and that was Maryam Bint e Imran(مریم بنت عمران).
And likewise we find in the Quran that Allah سبحانه وتعالى tells us about Zakaria(زکریاؑ),
that every time, he entered into Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی), he would find Maryam Binte Imran(مریم بنت عمران) there.
And likewise, we find in the Sunnah(سنۃ), the Prophet ﷺ telling us about
the Prophet Yahya( یحیٰؑ), the son of Zakaria(زکریاؑ ) and the prophet Eesa Ibne Maryam( عيسٰى ابن مریمؑ ) and Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی),
for in the Hadith(حدیث) of Al Haris al Ashari(حارث الاشعری) reported by Imam Ahmed(امام احمد), the Prophet ﷺ says that
Allah commanded Yahya bin Zakaria( یحی بن زکریا) with five commands
that he acts upon it, and that he commands the children of Israel to act upon it.
But Yahya Bin Zakaria(یحی بن زکریا) was slow to command the children of Israel to act upon it.
So Allah commanded Eesa Ibne Maryam(عيسٰى ابن مریم) to tell Yahya bin Zakaria(یحی بن زکریا) either command the children of Israel with it,
or I will command the children of Israel with it.
The Prophet ﷺ  tells us that Yahya bin Zakaria(یحی بن زکریا) says;
I'm afraid if you are to tell the children of Israel before me;
to his cousin, Eesa Ibne Maryam علیہ السلام, another prophet of Allah,
I am afraid if you were to tell them before me, then Allah عزوجل will either cause the earth to swallow me up or will punish me.
So Yahya bin Zakaria(یحی بن زکریا) gathers the people; the Prophet ﷺ says, in Bait-Al-Maqdas(بیت المقدس).
So the Masjid(مسجد) is filled.
And they're sitting there and then he tells them about Allah's commands,
five commands that of Tawheed(توحید) and Prayer and Fasting and Charity and Zikr(ذکر).
Then the Prophet ﷺ says; And I add to this five commands, and the Prophet ﷺ mentioned As-Sam’aa Wa Ta'aa(السمع وطاعۃ) and Jihad(جہاد) and Hijrah(ھجرۃ).
نعم
And then, of course we find that because the Jews, the children of Israel, didn't obey their prophets,
they killed Yahya ibne Zakaria علیہ السلام according to the books of tafseer(تفسیر), and they attempted to kill the Prophet Eesa عليه السلام,
but as Allah said they neither killed him nor crucified him but Allah raised him unto Him.
Than Allah سبحانه وتعالى then sends the Romans to destroy Masjid Al-Aqsa(مسجد الاقصٰی) in the year 70 after Eesa Ibn-e-Maryam عليه السلام.
And then history continues and Jahiliya(جاہلیہ) fills the earth,
until Allah سبحانه وتعالى sends as a mercy to all the worlds; the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ.
And in the revelation of the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ;
reference after reference to this Masjid Al-Aqsa(مسجد الاقصٰی) into these lands, as we quoted some and as we'll quote a few more.
For instance, a Surah(سورۃ) which I think all of us have memorized,
وَ التِّیْنِ وَ الزَّیْتُوْنِ ۝ وَ طُوْرِ سِیْنِیْنَ ۝ وَ هٰذَا الْبَلَدِ الْاَمِیْنِ۝
By the fig and the olive.
The fig refers to Damascus, and the olive refers to Jerusalem.
Damascus being the place where the prophet Eesaعليه السلام will come at the end of time,
and Jerusalem being the place where he used to give dawah unto.
وَطُوْرِ سِیْنِیْنَ۝
And the Mount Sinai, where the prophet Musa عليه السلام received revelation.
وَ هٰذَا الْبَلَدِ الْاَمِیْن۝
then this secure city, meaning Mecca, where the Prophet ﷺ received revelation.
Likewise, a very famous passage in Surah Noor(سورۃ النور),
even the passage is general, has been understood by some of the Salaf(سلف) to be specific where Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
فِیْ بُیُوْتٍ اَذِنَ اللّٰهُ اَنْ تُرْفَعَ وَ یُذْكَرَ فِیْهَا اسْمُهٗۙ
In certain homes or houses of worship where Allah سبحانه وتعالى has permitted that His name will be announced and be mentioned there.
Ikrama(عکرمہ), the student of the prophet's companion Ibn Abbas رضی اللہ عنہ
the Tabiee(تابعی), Ikrama(عکرمہ) says;
These places of worship are the Kaaba(کعبہ) and Masjid-E-Quba(مسجدِ قبا) and the Masjid(مسجد) of Madina and the Masjid of Bait-Al-Maqdas(بیت المقدس), meaning Masjid Al-Aqsa(مسجد الاقصٰی).
And likewise, the many Hadith(حدیث) of the Prophet ﷺ , which we've cited a number of those.
And so the Prophet ﷺ, from his practical Seerah(سیرۃ), and from the revelation which He revealed,
connected him to the prophets, and connected him to Bait-Al-Maqdas(بیت المقدس).
And so therefore upon the Prophet ﷺ life, he prepared the Muslims to take Bait-Al-Maqdas(بیت المقدس),
because Tawheed(توحید) has to be completed and this message confirms the other Messages, the Messengers.
So we find that the Prophet ﷺ in the eighth year of Hijrah(ھجرۃ), has this battle of Mota(موتہ),
which he sends 3000s of his companions in order to fight the Christian Romans, the Byzantines.
And then Mota(موتہ) is near what we now is area in Jordan called Petra and Mota(موتہ) is near that area.
So he sends as incharge of this army, Zaid ibne Harisa(زید ابن حارثہ).
And afterwards he says that if Zaid ibne Harisa (زید ابن حارثہ) is to die, then Jafar Ibn-E-Abi Talib(جعفر ابن ابی طالب) is to lead the companions, in this battle.
And if Jaffer Ibn-Abi-Talib(جعفر ابن ابی طالب ) is to die, then Abdullah Bin Rawaha(عبداللہ بن رواحہ) is to lead the companions.
And so the battle continues; 3000 of the Sahaba(صحابہ) fight the Christian Romans,
and Zaid Ibn E Harisa(زید ابن حارثہ) is given Shahadah(شہادۃ) and then Jaffer Ibn Abi Talib(جعفر ابن ابی طالب) is given shahada(شہادۃ)
and then Abdullah bin Rawaha(عباللہ بن رواحہ) has given Shahada(شہادۃ).
And then Allah سبحانه وتعالى decrees that Khalid Ibn Waleed(خالد بن ولید) leads the battle, and they defeat the Romans.
Now the Romans and the other Arab allies were not satisfied with this, so they prepare even a greater army now to invade Madina.
So when the Prophet ﷺ gets word of this, he commands all the believers to go out and to fight the Romans,
and he goes out with 30,000 of his companions, leading them himself for the battle of Tabuk(تبوک)
and Allah سبحانه وتعالى describes this battle of Tabuk(تبوک), the journey to the Battle of Tabuk(تبوک) in Surah Toba(سورہ توبہ),
because the hypocrites were exposed by not going forth in this battle, by staying back in Madina.
And Allah سبحانه وتعالى describes to us, the severe heat in which they went forth from Madina to Tabuk(تبوک)
which is the furthest northern region of Arabia, next to Syria, and Ash-Sham(الشام) areas.
And the Prophet ﷺ stayed there for a month, and the Christians among the Byzantines, the Europeans and their Arab allies, are afraid to show up.
So the Prophet ﷺ has returned, but yes there was no battle, but the fear of the Roman army is now broken amongst the Muslims,
just like now the Americans; Everybody's Muslim world is fear to the Americans, right?
When the one battle will come and their Might is broken, then the fear of that army and their military force will come to an end.
But the Prophet ﷺ is not satisfied with that.
So then he commands, in the final year of his life, just prior to his death, that Usama(اسامہ), the son of Zaid(زید),
Zaid Bin Harisa's(زید بن حارث ) son who was died in that battle, to lead an army against the Byzantines.
And he commands them that they place that they should go forth until they place their troops in Al Balqa(البلقاء).
However, the Prophet ﷺ dies.
The Prophet ﷺ dies, and Abu Bakar(ابوبکرؓ) is the Khalifah(خلیفۃ).
And a new issue occurs, that the Arabs apostated.
So what to do?
We have an army ready to go forth, and we have Arabia now as apostated.
The Sahabah(صحابہ) told Abu Bakar(ابوبکرؓ), we need these, every single man to fight the apostates.
They will deal with Ash-Sham(الشام).
Abu Bakr(ابوبکرؓ) says, By Allah, I will not send back an army which the Prophet ﷺ  has tied its banner to go forth.
And he says that even if the dogs of Madina were to enter into Madina,
because there are no more men there, the wild dogs and bite upon the legs of the Mothers of the Believers.
And among the Mothers of the Believers is his daughter, Aisha رضی اللہ عنھا, I will not send this army back.
So they go forth.
And then Abu Bakr(ابوبکرؓ) used to say,
It is more beloved to me that I take over a small village in Ash-Sham(الشام); Then I take over a big city in Iraq
because of this, as being the blessed land.
And then in the time of Umar Ibn Khattab(عمربن الخطابؓ), the conquest of Ash-Sham(الشام) continues,
and the armies are sent forth 12,000 of the Sahabah(صحابہ), led by the Amin(امین), the trustworthy of this Ummah(امۃ), Abu Ubeda Amr Bin Jarah(ابو عبیدہ بن الجراح),
and three other armies with them, one led by Yazeed Bin Abi Sufyan(یزید بن ابی سفیان),
and one by Amr Bin Al Aas(عمرو بن العاص) and one by Sharhabeel Bin Hasana(شرحبیل بن حسنہ).
And they conquer parts of Syria like Damascus and Hums(حمص) and parts of Palestine.
And in the year 13, there's a great battle of Ajnadeen(اجنادین) where the Sahabah(صحابہ) take over Palestine.
And then after that, you have the Battle of Yarmook (یرموک).
And this is a strange thing about the Battle of Yarmook(یرموک), the leader of the Byzantines was the brother of Heraculis,
you know heracle, right?
As mentioned in Hadith(حدیث) of Sahih Bukhari(صحیح بخاری), he recognizes that the prophet is the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ and he says;
If I have the ability to go and wash his feet, I would do so.
But yet, even though he recognized the truth, he wanted to remain upon his dominion,
and even though he knew that he would lose his dominion, as was told to him by the interpreters of his dream,
that he still let his brother, to lead the battle, and he was directing the battle from northern Syria.
So the Muslims, they take over this land, but left is Jerusalem.
It is still not in the hands of the believers, and so they surround it for four months in the middle of winter,
until finally the inhabitants of Jerusalem seek Amaan(امان).
They seek to make a treaty with the Muslims,
as they tell the commander of the Muslims, Abu Ubeida Amr Bin Jarah(ابو عبیدہ بن الجراح),
we want to sue have treaty, but we want to go and make the treaty with your leader.
So Abu Ubedah(ابو عبیدہ) takes a group of these Christians to Madina.
When they get to Madina, they're surprised, because they come across Umar Ibn Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) and what is Umar(عمر) doing?
He is sleeping underneath a tree.
See, this is the khilafah(خلافۃ) upon the Minhaj Un Nubuwwa(منہاج النبوۃ).
This is the rulership upon the way of the prophethood.
And so Umar(عمر) then decides to go forth to Jerusalem.
And as Ibn Ul-Jozi(ابن الجوزی) tells us in his book of history that Umar Ibn Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) went forth riding on a red camel,
and we went with him with his servant.
And he and his servant used to exchange riding the camel.
One time Umar(عمر) would ride it, and then after a while, he would get off and walk with the camel.
And then his servant would ride the camel and back and forth.
And the Muslims go forth with Umar Ibn Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), the Sahabah(صحابہ) all go forth with Umar(عمر)
because this is the great event that's going to happen.
Bait-Al-Maqdas(بیت المقدس) is going to return to the Muslims.
And when Umar(عمر) approaches the city, what happens?
It is his servant, who is riding the camel, and Umar(عمر) is pulling the camel, by turns.
And Umar Ibn Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) comes from the Mount of Olives,
and when they reached the Mount of Olives, that place where Eesa Ibn Maryam عليه السلام, is reported in the four gospels
gave his sermon of the mount, the Muslim starts saying Allah Ho Akbar(اللہ اکبر),
because it is the Sunnah(سنۃ) of the Prophet ﷺ that whenever you ascend upon something to say Takbir(تکبیر),
and then whenever you descend to say Subhan Allah(سبحان اللہ).
And so, following this Sunnah(سنۃ), they start saying Allah Ho Akbar(اللہ اکبر).
So the mountain is now not called the mountain of Olives but it's called Jebel Al Mukbar(جبل المکبر) ,
or the mountain in which the Takbir (تکبیر) was made.
And Umar Ibn Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) enters into this, and he makes the treaty with the ruler and the head patriarch, the Christian leader there.
And when the Christian patriarch sees this.
He says;
انا دولتکم باقیۃ علی الدھر
Your nation will remain for all of times.
فدولۃ الظلم ساعۃ ودولۃ عدل القیامۃ ساعۃ
A nation of injustice and oppression will only last an hour,
but a nation of Justice will remain until the establishment of the hour.
This is what the leading Christian bishop said,
not like as is reported by, in this history of the Crusades, printed by Cambridge or Oxford University.
I forget, which one in two volumes by an author Steven Runciman,
who says that when Umar(عمر) entered into the city,
he began to utter the words when you see the abomination of desolation, spoken of by Daniel, which we'll come to in the end.
You know, we will come to the end, in the end of the lecture, In Sha Allah(ان شاءاللہ).
We'll talk about how the prophets talked about what will happen to Jerusalem at the end of time.
And one of the revelation given to the prophet Danial علیہ السلام
and also the Prophet Eesa Ibn E Maryam(عيسٰى ابن مریم), is that when you see this abomination of desolation,
meaning this evil thing in Jerusalem, they know the Day of Judgment is coming.
So this Christian author here in England writing this history of the Crusades lies and says,
the patriarch of Jerusalem said these words,
in other words, that the evil the Muslims are that evil which is coming before the end of time.
But as the Muslims historians report, they said, the opposite.
He said that your nation will remain for all time.
For the nation of injustice is for an hour, meaning their land, their nation
and the nation of justice, until the end of time.
Anyway, the point is, is that Umar Ibn Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) asks of the patriarch to show us the Masjid(مسجد) of Dawood عليه السلام; shows Masjid Al-Aqsa(مسجد الاقصٰی).
And the patriarch doesn't want to show him Masjid Al-Aqsa(مسجد الاقصٰی).
He tries to avoid showing him that place.
And eventually he brings him to the hill where Masjid Al-Aqsa(مسجد الاقصٰی) is,
and Umar Ibn Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) says Allah Ho Akbar(اللہ اکبر).
This is what the Masjid(مسجد) that of Dawood عليه السلام, which The Messenger of Allah ﷺ described to us, he made Isra(اسریٰ) to,
Because don't forget that when the Prophet made Isra(اسریٰ), and he made Maeraj(معراج).
The Quraish(قریش) say, the Maeraj(معراج) is Okay, you go to the heaven, they don't believe in this in the first place,
but Isra(اسریٰ) something tangible.
How can you go to Mecca and Jerusalem back in a single night, when it takes our caravans four months to make the journey one way?
So then the Prophet ﷺ; Allah made for him a vision, where he actually described for them how Masjid Al-Aqsa(مسجد الاقصٰی) and how the Masjid(مسجد) looks like.
So when Umar(عمر) is there, he says Allahu Akbar (اللہ اکبر).
This is the Masjid(مسجد) of Dawood عليه السلام, which our Prophet has described for us.
And he made Isra(اسریٰ) to, he could see the same description the Prophet ﷺ gave to him.
And he noticed that, at the Mehrab(محراب) of the Prophet Dawoodعليه السلام,
that the Christian Romans, this is from the the ignorance of the Christians, that in order to show their animosity, to the Jews,
they used to throw their refuse, their trash, meaning, like the excrement and so forth in this in this area, the Masjid(مسجد) of Al Aqsa(الاقصٰی),
even though their prophet, the prophet Eesa عليه السلام, preached from there, but this is from their ignorance.
So Umar Ibn Khattaab رضی اللہ عنہ, takes off his cloak and begins to carry off the refuse and clean the Masjid(مسجد) area.
And the Sahaba, upon seeing this, begin to do the same, until they clean off the Mehrab(محراب) of the Prophet Dawood عليه السلام.
So Umar Ibn Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) stands and prays two Raka'ah(رکعۃ)'s and begins to recite Surah Saad(سورۃ ص).
Why Surah Saad(سورۃ ص)?
Because it is the Surah(سورۃ) in which Allah سبحانه وتعالى mentions Dawood(داؤد) at the Mehrab(محراب),
and also it is the Surah(سورۃ) in which Allah سبحانه وتعالى tells Dawood(داؤد), we have made you a Khalifa(خلیفۃ),
so judge amongst the people with justice and Umar(عمر) is that Khalifa(خلیفۃ) now.
And then he asked Ka'ab Al-Ahbar(کعب احبار), the Al-Ahbar(کعب احبار) the Jewish rabbi, who becomes a Muslim, he's from the Tabaeen(تابعین).
Ka'ab Al-Ahbar(کعب احبار) was a Jewish rabbi in Yemen who becomes a Muslim, and was from the Tabaeen(تابعین) and was amongst the army that conquers Jerusalem.
So Umar(عمر) goes to Ka'ab(کعب) and says, point to me the rock in which the prophet ﷺ made his Maeraj(معراج) from.
So Ka'ab(کعب) points to him the place.
And then Umar(عمر) says, Where shall we build the Masjid(مسجد) then?
Because the Masjid(مسجد) was destroyed by the Romans in the year 70, and they used to throw their trash there.
So now there's been no prayer there for how many years now, at least 600 years, or little less than 600 years.
And so what does Ka'ab(کعب) say?
Build the Masjid(مسجد) behind the rock
so that when we make Salah(صلاۃ) from Jerusalem, we will face the Qibla(قبلہ) of the previous prophets, and we'll face the Qibla(قبلہ) of our Qibla(قبلہ), the Mecca.
Umar(عمر) says;
واحیت الیہودیہ یا کعب
You resemble Jews; Oh, Ka'ab(کعب).
No, we will put this behind us.
For that Qibla(قبلہ) has been abrogated.
So he builds his Masjid(مسجد), Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی) before the rock.
And the Sahabah(صحابہ) then used to visit, as I mentioned, Ibn Umar(ابن عمر) went there and among the Sahabah(صحابہ) who settled there.
And in fact, Abu Darda(ابو درداء), one of the prophets companions, Abu darda(ابو درداء) and Salman Al Farsi(سلمان فارسی) had a closeness together in Madina,
but Salman al Farsi(سلمان فارسی) went with the Muslims who conquered Iraq and Persia.
But Abu Darda(ابو درداء) loved Salman Al Farsi(سلمان فارسی), there was a bond between them and Madina given to them
but Abu Darda(ابو درداء) was in Ash-Sham(الشام).
So he writes Salman Al Farsi(سلمان فارسی) a letter saying, come to the holy lands.
So Salman(سلمان) writes him back.
He said; It is not the lands that makes a man holy, but it is His righteous actions that makes a man holy.
But you see, the Sahabah(صحابہ) wanted the other Sahabah(صحابہ) to come there, and some of them live there.
There's something which I forgot to mention, which is very touching to the heart,
what happens in Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی) when Umar Ibn Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) is there.?
You know that the Prophet's companion, Bilal رضی اللہ عنہ used to do the Azaan(اذان) for the Prophet ﷺ,
and upon his death, he refused to do the Azaan(اذان) anymore,
because for him to say the Azaan(اذان) after the Prophet ﷺ death was something too difficult for him to do again.
But yet Bilal رضی اللہ عنہ was with the army of Umar(ؑعمر) that enters into Jerusalem with the delegation of Umar(ؑعمر).
And so when it comes time for Salah(صلاۃ), after they've cleaned Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی),
Umar(ؑعمر) goes to Bilal(بلالؓ) and says؛
یا بلال قم فازن
stand and make the Azaan(اذان).
So Bilal(بلالؓ) says the Azaan رضی اللہ عنہ and all the Sahabah(صحابہ) begin to cry
because they remember the Azaan(اذان) that he would be said from the Prophet’s Masjid ﷺ.
Now the Sahabah(صحابہ) of course, lived in Jerusalem.
Some settled there, but they also settled elsewhere upon the earth.
Teaching the Muslims, whether it was in Iraq or Persia or Egypt or elsewhere, they spread throughout the lands.
And of course, then the Sahabah(صحابہ), because of the plottings of the Jews, Abdullah Bin Saba(عبداللہ بن سبا), the Yahudi(یہودی),
certain fittan(فتن) occurred between them.
But the Prophet ﷺ said that one day he was standing on his member, giving a Khutbah(خطبہ),
and he sees his grandson, Al Hassan(الحسن), who is a small boy, playing on the Mimber(ممبر), he says;
This son of mine is a Sayyad(سیّد), a leader, a master, a noble person and Allah will bring between him to rectify two great groups of the Muslims.
And in the year 40, when Al Hasan(الحسن) was Khalifah(خلیفہ) and Muawiah(معاویہ) was also another Ameer(امیر),
Al Hassan(ٓالحسن) in order to make peace between the Muslims, he steps down from the Khilafah(خلافہ) and gives it to Muawiah(معاویہ).
So where does Muawiah(معاویہ) take the Baiyah(بیعہ) from?
He takes baiyah(بیعہ) from Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی).
The Muslims give him Baiyah(بیعہ) in Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی), and then Bani Ummayah(بنی امیہ) has its force, its center of its power, in Damascus.
And you find that the Khulafa of Bani Umayyah(بنی امیہ) come often to Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی) and they do certain things.
Among them is Abdul Malak(عبد الملک), one of the Khulafa(خلفاء) of Bani Ummayah(بنی امیہ).
Who, during his time, wants to see Jerusalem built up because the Muslims now have much, much money from Jihad(جہاد).
So he wants to see Jerusalem beautified and built up, to its greatest.
So he builds Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی) again, rebuilds it and he builds the Dome of the Rock.
And he puts in charge of it two of the scholars of his time, Rija Bin Haiwa(رجاء بن حیوٰۃ) and Abdullah Bin Salam(عبداللہ بن سلام) or Abdul Salam(عبدالسلام).
And when they finish building it up, they write a letter to the Khalifa Abdul Malik (خلیفہ عبدالملک) in Damascus.
They said to him; We have built it in such a way that nobody can say anything that there's anything else to build,
and 100,000 dinars are left, so you as the Ameer- Ul Momin(امیر المومن), spend it, wherever you think is best for the Muslims.
Abdul Malik(عبدالملک) sends him a letter back saying; I am giving you these 100,000 dinars for the good job that you two have done.
The two scholars write back;
They said, it is more befitting for us
than we take our women's jewelry, their gold, and we use it to beautify this Masjid(مسجد) and our money, than to take this money.
In other words, we should not take any of this money, but we should rather take our own personal wealth and add it to this Masjid(مسجد).
So this shows us how the scholars and the leaders of the Muslims used to pay attention to Bait Ul Maqdas(بیت المقدس)
and in fact Umar bin Abdul Aziz(عمر بن عبدالعزیز), when he became the Khalifa(خلیفہ) and he returned government back to the way of the way of the prophethood,
منہاج النبوۃ
And he was a Khalifah(خلیفہ) only for two years, only for two years and he reformed the Ummah(امۃ) only two years.
He told all his governors to go to Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی), pray to rakaats(رکعۃ) and to give an oath that they would obey him and be just amongst the Muslims.
Now the Muslims, then, of course, left the Sunnah(سنۃ); They left the message of the Qur'an; They declined.
The Shia took over and then the Crusaders come, and they take Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی) from the believers in the fifth century.
But Allah سبحانه وتعالى raises for this Ummah(امۃ) the likes of Nuruddin Zangi(نورالدین زنگی).
This Muslim leader in Mosul(موصل) in northern Iraq, who puts it upon himself to return back the lands of the Muslims from the Christians, from the Crusaders
and Nuruddin Zangi(نورالدین زنگی), conquers over 70 of the Crusader forts castles and many cities,
but his wish is to see Jerusalem conquered.
So he builds a Mimber(ممبر).
And the Muslims are surprised, you're building a Mimber(ممبر) for Bait Ul Maqdas(بیت المقدس), and yet we still haven't even come close to that.
He said, Yes, I've built this Mimber(ممبر) so that it's may one day will stand upon it in Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی) when it's returned to the Muslims.
And then, of course, Nuruddin Zangi(نورالدین زنگی) Allah decrees that he dies; He is actually he's killed by a Batoni(باطنی) one of the Shia.
He's poisoned; That's why he's called Nur Ud-Din Shaheed(نور الدیں الشہید), the martyr,
but his student and the one who was raised in his household, Salahuddin Ayubi(صلاح الدین ایوبی) continues the return of the holy lands from the Crusaders.
And when Salahuddin Ayubi(صلاح الدین ایوبی) is described, is described by his judge, Ibn Shidad(ابن شداد), in his history,
and likewise, is quoted by the other historians, like Ibn Kathir(ابن کثیر) and others,
when he enters into Bait Ul Maqdas(بیت المقدس), when they take it from the Christians,
he sends the command to Damascus, bring us the Mimber(ممبر) of Noor Ud Din(نورالدین).
And they bring that Mimber(ممبر) back, and the Khatib(خطیب) stands upon it.
And they give the Khutbah Al Jumah(خطبہ الجمعہ), the first Jummah(جمعہ) back in Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی) after 70 years in the possession of the Christians.
Someone says even the Christians have put a major cross on top of Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی), on top of the Dome of the rock.
This Mimber(ممبر), as a side point to know,
was remained in Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی), and the Khatib(خطیب)s gave Khutba(خطبہ) after Khutba(خطبہ) on this, until 1967.
When the Australian Christian fanatic went there and fire bombed that Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی) and burnt down the Mimber(ممبر).
And that's why now all we can see is the Mimber(ممبر), just if we see a picture of it.
Now, of course, the Muslims, you know, after taking Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی), they remained there,
until modern history, when Allah سبحانه وتعالى decreed.
I can have 10 more minutes. It should be OK Tayeb(طیب), Sure.
So they want me to end the lecture in 10 minutes.
So if I have to end then if you get angry.
So then Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجدالاقصٰی) is taken from the Muslims.
In the first event towards that is in 1798, when Napoleon takes Egypt, and one of his aims is that he wants to take Jerusalem,
to send all the Jews from Europe into Jerusalem.
Napoleon fails, but then in 1882 the British take Egypt,
and then finally, in World War One, with the fall of the Usmani Khilafa(خلافت عثمانیہ).
General Allenby, the British General, enters into Jerusalem and ascends upon the Mount of Olives and says;
Now the Crusades have ended,
and then the Christians the British control, not only Jerusalem, but they also control the surrounding lands, being Egypt and Iraq,
and then they leave it and they give it to the Jews.
And the State of Israel comes and the history we know the rest, in 48 the State of Israel, 67 they take Jerusalem
and the Intifada(انتفاضہ) which we now seeing.
And we don't have time to get into those details.
But what do we want to talk about now?
We want to now move to another topic, even very quickly, about the quality of those people who are now in Jerusalem.
The qualities of the Jews;
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has mentioned in the Qur'an over and over their qualities,
and I have many passages which I would like to quote, but unfortunately we don't have time.
So what I will do is, I'll suffice, I'll quote to Sayyed Qutub(سید قطب), who has a very lovely essay, which he wrote رحمت اللہ علیہ called;
معرِکَتنُا مع یہود
Or our struggle with the Jews.
So I'll just read a paragraph or two from it.
He says, Sayyed Qutub(سید قطب) begins his essay by saying;
the Muslim Ummah(امۃ) continues to suffer from the same jewish machinations and double dealing which discomfited the early Muslims,
but the Muslim Ummah(امۃ) today does not, one must say, with great regret, utilize those Quranic directives and this divine guidance regarding these problems.
And then he mentions some certain passages.
He says, the Muslim Ummah(امۃ) does not take advantage of the Islamic sources which its Salaf(سلف) used.
Only in this way were the Salaf(سلف), meaning the Sahabah(صحابہ), able to overcome jewish conspiracy and double dealing in Madina.
And thus did the religion of Islam arise, and thus was the Muslim Ummah(امۃ) born.
The Jews continue, through their wickedness and double dealing to lead this Muslim Ummah(امۃ) away from its religion
and to alienate it from its Qur'an.
They do this in order to prevent the Ummah(امۃ) from utilizing his traditional Qur'anic weapons and its perfect Qur'ani readiness for this struggle.
The jews are so cure, so long as this Muslim Ummah(امۃ) is stranged from the sources of its real power and the roots of its pure knowledge.
In other words, as long as we stay away from the Qur'an, they will continue to have the upper hand over us.
Now the lecture must come to an end, so let us quickly talk about the future.
What does the future hold for the Ummah(امۃ)?
Just like the Prophet ﷺ, described to us and as Allah described to us, the history of the prophets regarding Jerusalem and Palestine,
likewise the revelations of Allah's Prophet tells us about the last days
which we quoted one Hadith(حدیث), the Hadith (حدیث) Ibn Hawalah Al-Azdi (ابن حوالة الأزدي) Concerning the last days of Jerusalem.
That this Ummah(امۃ) will return to having Jerusalem as its place of power and its center.
This is a promise which Allah عزوجل has given to us upon the tongue of His Prophet, the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ.
The situation in which we are living today in, must come to an end,
because falsehood must go away and truth must remain.
The question which we should ask ourselves are we this part of the Ummah(امۃ) which will be honored by seeing that day,
or are we still carrying that portion of a sin, and so we will remain to live under the stimulation till the end of our days?
That's the question we should ask ourselves.
But whether that Jerusalem will return to the Muslims is a foregone conclusion.
It needs no discussion because it is a promise in Allah scripture, and is a promise upon the tongue of the Prophet Muhammad ﷺ.
In order for us to return to Jerusalem, we must return to the Qur'an, as Sayyed Qutub رحمتہ اللہ علیہ was quoting in that passage I read from him,
we must return to the Qur'an, and we must return to the Sunnah(سنۃ).
When we raise ourselves upon this true knowledge, then we will find Jerusalem will be in our hands.
Now however though, we should have glad tidings and feel very happy
because the signs of victory are appearing in front of us.
Yes, there are might be many, many difficulties and many, many trials and tribulations to come before us,
but you can sense and you can smell the victory, and I have a couple of anecdotes towards that.
When I was in college, when I was a freshman in 1981.
The Palestinian brothers used to have tables where they would want to stir up support for the cause of Palestine, as students do in all universities.
And I remember one day I was walking and in the University, in the Student Union, and I saw the table about Palestine and the slogans in Arabic,
but I was greatly saddened.
Why?
Because all the books on the table there were about mMarks and revolutionary thoughts.
And it was talking about you know, reactionary and it's all the dialog of you know, the left, you know.
And in fact, one of the sisters was sitting there, not only she did not have hijab on,
but she didn't care to wear a shirt.
She took a Ghutra(غطرۃ) like this, and she used it to cover herself, to show her, allegiance to Palestine.
And even though they were all Muslims,
they had a picture behind them of the Prophet Eesa عليه السلام crucified and with the background of Masjid al Aqsa or the Dome of the Rock.
So I remember talking to these Palestinians, I was saying to them, what's this?
And we had a discussion, I use to say to them, you know, Islam is the only way you're going to return Phalistine(فلسطین) back.
And you know what they did, they laughed at me, and they thought I was crazy.
Now, when you look at the video clips of and this was 1981 now we're in 2001 only 20 years right.
Now, when you look at the video clips of an Intifada(انتفاضہ), what do you find?
You find the slogan of Allah Ho Akbar(اللہ اکبر).
See the difference?
This is a sign of the coming victory of Islam.
Yes, it's not quite there yet, but the fact that the Islamic banner, the fact that the youth of Palestine now are raising the banner of;
لا اله الا الله محمد الرسول الله
should bring great happiness to the heart of every single Muslim,
because just 20 years ago, you could not even hear that slogan, or if it was there, it was very low in terms of its intensity, or the volume of his intensity.
The second incident or anecdote, was just before I came to here, there was a video program which I wanted to bring here, but I was unable to bring,
which was shown on public television in the United States,
where they were talking about how the Jews now are working toward destroying, with the Christian fundamentals, destroying Masjid Al Aqsa(مسجد الاقصٰی),
and to build what they say the temple back because they think the Messiah will come.
And perhaps during the question answer, we might delve into it.
I had a part of the lecture but because of the time; We have to put it, to the side.
Anyway, the commentator on the program, who was a Jew himself, says this in the end of the program.
He says; he calls upon the American people.
He says you must save your ally.
Because he said, the days of Israel are very short indeed if they continue upon this path.
So this is a promise which Allah, سبحانه وتعالى , has given us.
Victory will be ours.
The question we need to ask ourselves it's whether Allah عزوجل will make us from that generation which will see the victory,
or will we not enjoy the fruit of that due to our sinfulness and the generation that might come after us or the one that might come after that us will be it.
Now somebody might say, okay brother Ali(علی) how long do we have to wait?
I remember reading and with this, I'll close just to instill hope in our hearts.
I remember reading an interview which was done by Al Bayan magazine here in London, Muntazar
With Shaykh Ahmed Yasin(شیخ احمد یٰس) a few months ago,
where they asked Shaykh Ahmed Yasin(شیخ احمد یٰس) the brother, the Shaikh, who's leader of Hamas,
how long will this conflict last?
He said, I see it not lasting very much longer.
And he took it from a lesson from the Qur'an.
He said, You know that Allah سبحانه وتعالى required upon the Jews to wander for 40 years
in order to make that generation of bondage and slavery which lived amongst the Mushrikeen(مشرکین) to die,
he said that the worst generation in our Palestinian history was the generation which lost Palestine in 1948.
He said 40 years didn't complete, but in 1987 you'll have the First Intifada(انتفاضہ).
And he says, I cannot imagine that another 40 years will not pass except that Bait-Ul-Maqdas(بیت المقدس) and Phalistine will be return to the Muslims.
He says; In the end of his interview, he said,
you might have to add 10 years or subtract 10 years, or add five or subtract five, but it won't be more than this.
So if you think about it, from 1987 and add 40 years is, how many for the next generation to come, 2027.
Okay, we are now in 2001 so maybe just 25 years.
So perhaps the young boys in this audience might be from those Mujahideen(مجاہدین), who will be there to enter into Bait Ul Maqdas(بیت المقدس),
and on that day, the believers will be happy with the victory of Allah.
أقول قولي هذا واستغفر الله لي ولكم
سُبْحَانَکَ اللّٰھُمَّ وَبِحَمْدِکَ اَشْھَدُ اَنْ لَّآ اِلٰہَ اِلَّآ اَنْتَ اَسْتَغْفِرُکَ وَاَتُوْبُ اِلَیْکَ
And again my apology as we couldn't get into the other topics,
but perhaps in the question answer, we can address some of the other matters,
جَزَاكُمُ اللَّهُ خَيْرًا، السلام علیکم